Guide to the Ephemera Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ephemera collection
1792-1992
MS 1879
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.25
The collection contains primarily political, military, and commemorative ephemera, including but not limited to pins, ribbons, buttons, cuff links, and medals.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Coins and Medals, Yale University Art Gallery, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to Ephemera Collection is by appointment only. Contact the Head of Public Services or the Public Services Manager.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by type of material: Cloth, Metal, and Paper/Wood
Scope and Contents
The collection contains primarily political, military, and commemorative ephemera, including but not limited to pins, ribbons, buttons, cuff links, and medals.
Commemorative coins; Medals; Military decorations; Political collectibles; Souvenirs (Keepsakes)
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The collection is arranged by type of material: cloth, metal, and paper/wood. The small number of items that do not fit this categorization have generally been left with the materials with which they are associated. The vast majority of objects are metal. Most of the metal objects are pins, though there are also coins, jewelry, buttons, cuff links, and other items. Fragile and oversized metal items have been removed, housed in appropriate storage, and placed at the end of the metal category. Many of the non-pin metal objects have also been placed at the end of the category.
  Each category is arranged in groups. The groups from the metal category are awards, commemorative (including souvenirs), military, organizations, personal collections, political, social issues, and Yale University. Some of the same groups constitute the arrangement of the cloth and paper/wood categories.
  - Cloth
    - General, 1876, 1890-1926, 1941, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 5)
    - Military
      - General, 1879-1896, 1914, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
        General note
        See also: Box 12, Folder 26 - 32 See also: Box 13, Folder 33 - 35
      - "Campaigns and Decorations", undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Spanish-American War, 1904-1923 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Numismatics' conventions ribbons, 1963-1991 (Box 2, Folder 9 - 12)
    - Political, 1892-1910, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Metal
    - General, 1919, 1935-1940, undated (Box 3)
    - Awards, 1824, 1889, 1898, 1909, undated (Box 3)
    - Commemorative [including souvenirs]
      - General, 1876-1937, undated (Box 3–4)
      - Columbus, Christopher, voyage to America quadricentennial, 1892 (Box 4)
      - Dewey, George, return from Spanish-American War, 1898-1899, undated (Box 4)
      - Edward VII, King of the United Kingdom, coronation, 1902 (Box 4)
      - Expositions and world's fairs, 1876, 1893-1894, 1939 (Box 4)
      - Grant, General Ulysses S., monuments honoring, 1897, 1899, 1922 (Box 4)
      - Hudson, Henry [including Hudson-Fulton celebration and commemoration of the discovery of Lake Champlain], 1909 (Box 4–5)
      - Identification badges, 1902-1916, 1933, 1940, 1967, undated (Box 5)
      - Jamestown tercentennial, 1907 (Box 5)
      - Liberty Bell, undated (Box 5)
      - Maryland Memorial Day, 1895 (Box 5)
      - Pan-American Exposition, 1901 (Box 5)
      - Peace celebrations, 1878, 1899 (Box 5)
      - Plymouth, Massachusetts tercentennial, 1920-1921 (Box 5)
    - Military
      - General, 1896, 1901, 1912, 1915, undated (Box 5)
      - Wars
        - Napoleon III wars, 1859, 1862-1863 (Box 5)
        - Spanish-American War, 1898-1928 (Box 5)
        - World War I, 1914-1918, undated (Box 6–10)
        - World War II, 1940-1945, undated (Box 10)
      - Countries
        - Austria-Hungary, 1854, 1867, 1889-1908, 1914-1918, undated (Box 11, Folder 14 - 21)
        - Belgium, 1939-1946 (Box 11, Folder 22)
        - Czechoslovakia, undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
        - France, 1792, 1870-1871, undated (Box 12, Folder 24 - 25)
        - Germany [includes patches], 1934-1942, undated (Box 12, Folder 26 - 32)
        - Germany [includes patches], 1935-1940, undated (Box 13, Folder 33 - 35)
        - Great Britain, undated (Box 13, Folder 36)
        - Holland, undated (Box 13, Folder 37)
        - Italy, undated (Box 13, Folder 38 - 39)
        - Loose materials, undated (Box 13)
    - Organizations [including Elks, Shriners, A.F.L.-C.I.O., Red Cross, United Service Organizations, Hadassah, and others], 1876, 1899-1931, 1946-1950, undated (Box 14)
    - Personal collections
      - Morris, Charles G. [primarily materials associated with ice cream manufacturers], 1909-1922, undated (Box 14–15)
      - Williams, C. B. [primarily commemorative materials], 1873-1919, undated (Box 15)
    - Political
      - Ajello-Eisenhower, 1896, 1912, 1956, 1992, undated (Box 15)
      - Ella-Lehman, 1903, 1908, 1917, 1932, 1980, undated (Box 16)
      - Lieberman-McKinley, 1972, undated (Box 16)
      - McKinley-Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1974, 1984, undated (Box 16)
      - Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1938, 1940, undated (Box 17)
      - Roosevelt, Theodore-Williams, 1904-1905, 1928, undated (Box 17)
      - Willkie, Wendell, 1940, undated (Box 18–19)
      - Willkie, Wendell-Zelinsky, unidentified, 1912, undated (Box 19)
    - Social issues [includes women's suffrage, abortion, peace, the environment, homosexuality, and mental illness], undated (Box 19)
    - Yale University, 1984, undated (Box 19)
    - Fragile and oversized materials, 1899-1909, undated (Box 19–20)
    - Non-pin materials [buttons, coins, and jewelry], 1851-1864, 1899, 1908-1960, undated (Box 21)
  - Paper/Wood
    - General, 1937, undated (Box 22, Folder 40)
    - Commemorative, 1889, 1937 (Box 22, Folder 41)
    - Military
      - "Goeben- und Breslau-Kameradschaft 4.-6. Juni 1932 in Wilhelmshaven" (Box 22, Folder 42)
      - Insignia of World War I, undated (Box 22, Folder 43)
    - Organizations [Red Cross], 1918 (Box 22, Folder 44)
    - Political, 1913, 1936, 1971-1972, 1987 (Box 22, Folder 45)
    - "Radio photo message...during period of nearest approach of Mars to the Earth", 1924 August (Box 22, Folder 46)
  - Other materials
    See: Box 21